>> Hi, good morning everyone.
My name is [indiscernible] and I
am from the [indiscernible]
Accessibility team,
one of the senior
program managers here.
I have Sean Marihugh
[phonetic] here from the
[indiscernible] Organization.
He's from the [indiscernible]
Accessibility Team today.
He's going to present and
cover a topic for the webinar,
and today's topic is about
Creating Accessible Content
in Word and PowerPoint.
The format of the webinar
is going to be an hour long,
and the last 15 minutes
we will go ahead and take
any questions you have.
So continue posting all your
questions in the Q&A window here,
and I'll surface [phonetic]
them towards the end.
With that said,
let's kickstart the webinar.
Shawn, over to you.
Thanks.
>> Sounds good.
Thank you [indiscernible].
Good morning, everyone.
Thanks for those of you
who have joined so far.
As [indiscernible] mentioned,
I am going to cover some tips
on creating accessible
content, mostly focused
on Word and PowerPoint,
but whenever possible,
I'll try to bring
it out to other products
too like Outlook, some
of our online offerings and
even tools like accessibility
inside [phonetic]
briefly near the end.
Again, this is all just to
cover some of the basics
of what you can do to make
your content more consumable
for people with disabilities.
But also, there's a lot of
great practices that, while
it's better from an
accessibility perspective,
it's also just better for
everyone consuming your content.
So I'll try to call out some
of those examples as well.
Just to give you an idea of
what we'll run through today -
I'll talk a little but
about what accessibility
really means, why it's such
an important topic, and
then I'll cover in the main
portion, I'll do several demos.
I have a sample document and
sample slides that we'll work
through and I'll just show
you how to do a lot these
of things on this list.
We'll first start by looking
at what the accessibility
checker is able to
do, I'll talk more
about that shortly.
And then there's a few
things the tool isn't able
to check for automatically,
but some other recommendations
we'd still have.
There's an option in Outlook
for request accessible content.
It shows up as a reminder
for anyone who's sending
you content that
they know you'd prefer it
be in an accessible format.
And then as I mentioned,
I'll briefly touch
on accessibility insights
before we get into some Q&A.
So let's go ahead
and jump right in.
I'm just going to be
working through this
slide and chipping away
at each of the
bullet points here.
When we're talking about
accessibility, we often
reference the number that one
in five people in the
world has a disability.
Now, disability is a spectrum.
There's just a wide
range of disability and
how it can impact folks.
But when we think about
designing content that is
accessible and meets the needs
of those one in five
people, it's also a great
experience for everyone.
But when we think about
delivering content to customers
or stakeholders with
that same figure -
let's imagine that one in five
of our stakeholders, one in five
of our customers
has a disability -
if we're not designing
things in content and
information and websites
and apps that don't meet their we
run the risk of excluding people.
Accessibility is all about
including and just building
some of those systems
and tools, helping you understand
the best practices and how to
deliver on accessibility.
I'm going to switch over
to my sample document
that I created today.
Change my office theme.
So I've created this document
on the Amazon Rainforest.
Just to give you an idea
of what's in here, there's
a table that has some information
about what percentage of the
Amazon Rainforest is
in each South American country,
some information on deforestation,
a few images, some content
on why all this matters and what
folks can do to get involved.
Then I have my bibliography
down at the very end.
So let's just do an overview
of what's in the document.
So I mentioned the
accessibility checker.
That's a feature in
Office that basically runs
a set of automated checks
against your content and
returns several results.
There's a few
ways to find this.
If you've used it
for a long time,
you may know that it's in
File, Info, Check for Issues,
then Check Accessibility.
But since it was introduced
there, it's now
a lot more discoverable in
a couple of other spots too.
So now in the Review tab,
there is just a button there
for Check Accessibility.
That's another way to
get to it so, again,
it's all about just making
it even more discoverable.
In the next area I want to
show, down in
the status bar, which is the
lower left corner of the window.
It has things like page numbers,
word count, etc., you may notice
that there's an item
that says accessibility
recommendations found.
Check here to investigate.
Now that's even maybe
even more discoverable, so
as I add content,
the status of that little icon
will change, and I can just
activate it right away to open
the accessibility checker.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Cool.
We now have our accessibility
checker results organized in
a few different ways.
You'll notice that there's
errors, things that the
tool is able to tell.
There are definitely issues
and things we should fix.
And then there's some
warnings, there are some other
best practices and then, as
I work through this, we'll
see a couple other categories
of issues come up as we
work through these items.
So first I did want to
start and talk a little
bit about text contrast.
So you may notice in this
deforestation section here,
I have some text that
I have intentionally made that
very hard to read, just as kind
of an exaggerated example.
But I have some text here
that's black text with a
dark blue highlight.
So it's pretty hard to read.
And the tool flags that as
having a color contrast issue.
Now, this is an exaggerated
example, but I do often see
in lots of documents
and content that authors use
text color and highlights
that are really similar and
so, for a user that's
maybe low vision,
it's a lot more difficult to
differentiate that text from
the background,
and in this example,
it's just very difficult for
everyone because it's such a -
there's not very
much contrast there.
So the accessibility checker
now let's you fix these things
inline.
Let's go ahead and expand each of
these and see what we can do so.
It selects the text for me.
You may notice that there's a
drop down in that list as well.
So if I select the drop
down, that gives
me the recommended actions
I can take just right away.
So I can change the font
color or I can change my
text highlight color.
In this case, the usual intent
of a highlight is just giving
the text highlight color.
So let's go ahead and change the
highlight from black to yellow.
That's pretty common.
As I change that, you'll
notice the error is now
cleared out of the list.
So that's one down.
As I talk about this, I'll also
reference some of the best
practices I mentioned earlier.
One of the things that's
really common, in emails
especially, so this
is where I'll get into Outlook
and other apps a little bit.
When you highlight some
text, it's often good to
indicate that information
with more than just
the color alone.
So in accessibility, that's
generally referred to using color
alone to convey information.
And so, oftentimes,
when you're highlighting something
or putting comments inline
and you're using things
like see in line, and
if you're using only colors,
only highlights to indicate
it can get a little bit lost.
So if you want to make sure that
people see this, select the text,
or the other option is
to use underline here.
I have a cat in my fact today.
Using an underline is just another
way to add some extra context
on how to differentiate
this information.
One other option is if you're
using lots of in-line comments
and emails, in addition
to using the color, using your
initials or the date is another
good way to indicate it.
I'll just give you an example.
Let's say I decided to do
that, where I put
my name, my initials, and the
date to indicate my comment.
So now I'm conveying that I
want to call attention to that
item in more than just color.
So those are always good
things to keep in mind.
Moving along here, I
mentioned that this document
has a couple images, and
so under my deforestation
heading and right before
the Why It Matters section,
I have a photo that
I put in here that's
a waterfall falling off
of a cliff and it's kind
of surrounded by jungle.
And so when we're thinking about
images, generally, there's a
couple different types.
There's things that we're really
intending to convey content.
In this case, our subject matter
is all about the Amazon Rainforest
and so, maybe this sort
of photo of something
in the jungle is a very
indicative of that environment
and so maybe I'd want
to keep that here.
When we're thinking about
images, it's important that
people be able to consume those.
And so oftentimes we
refer to what's called
"alternative text" for images.
And that's just really -- let's
show you what that looks like.
So when I select one
of these errors -
when my cat gets out
of the way here -
let's select one
of the errors here.
Picture 1,
it says missing alternative text.
Alternative text is basically a
description of the image that
captures the key take away.
And so for someone who is blind
or low vision, or is using
an assistive technology,
that technology would
read out the description
of the image when
they encounter it.
Similar to how a sighted
user might glance through
the email, see the image,
and get the take away
of what the image
is conveying, all text is a way
of conveying that to people
with disabilities as well.
So there's a couple
things we can do here.
So I'll just expand this
drop down and we can take
a look at some of the
options that are available.
So we can either have our
own description, where
we can type it out,
we can mark it as decorative.
I'll talk about
that in a minute.
And then there's these other
two options, one of them
is Learn more and Suggest
a description for me.
This is a cool new feature
that sends the image to
the computer vision service
that does its best guess of
describing what the image is.
This is a great
starting point.
Oftentimes, these do
pretty well at capturing
the intent of the image.
So let's give that a try.
So I'm going to tell it to
Suggest a description here.
So a couple things happened, in
my accessibility checker results,
under Errors, I have one fewer
error on Missing alternative text.
Then I have this new category of
Intelligent Services, and it tells
me that there's some Suggested
alt text in my document.
The reason it tells
us this is just as
an extra step to validate that
description is really correct.
So let's go ahead
and check that.
So Verify description.
It says,
"A large waterfall in a forest."
You'll notice that it
says, "Description
automatically generated."
Again, just indicating that
this was generated online.
Given my subject matter
here, talking about the
Amazon Rainforest, maybe
we should make this a
little more specific.
A large waterfall falling
off a cliff in a jungle.
And so I've added just a
little more context for someone
to really see why I
had this specific image
in here as opposed to the
description it suggested was
a waterfall in a forest.
That could kind of be
anywhere, and
so someone who is using
assistive technology is consuming
this document, they may
be confused about why
exactly that's in there.
So that extra layer of
specificity helps here.
Just for fun, there is an
option here, Donate your picture
for science and it helps
kind of train the image
recognition models.
So I can say, yes,
and that will upload my image.
And the confirmation it says here
is, "Your contribution will make
it easier for us to
describe images for blind
or low-vision users."
There's one more
image in our document.
So let's take a look at that.
So this case,
I have this section on here
are some ways to get
involved, and there's five
different options here.
There's this image here.
So my last bullet point is
"Donate to the World Wildlife
Fund," and then right below
that, I have an image of the
World Wildlife Fund logo.
So now we're getting into
some of the nuance of images.
So because I've
just called out
the World Wildlife Fund,
this image, one could
argue, isn't adding
any informative content
because the content that
it's adding is kind of
covered right above it.
One option is we could mark
the alternative text just a
World Wildlife Fund logo.
When we think about
the experience
of someone who is using
an assistive technology,
they might hear
out bullet number five, "Donate
to the World Wildlife Fund,"
and the next thing you hear
is "World Wildlife Fund logo."
Maybe that's just not the most
useful piece of information here.
So that's the other option
in the recommended actions
drop down I covered.
Mark as decorative,
so let's do that, and that
will just basically treat
it as an invisible object.
It's not conveying content -
just to avoid giving
someone too much redundant
information, so let's mark
it as decorative.
And, great, now our images and
all text are gone from this list.
While we're on the subject
of images, there's one more
thing that's calling out here.
Images or objects not
inline.
Let's take a look at that and
see what that's pointing to.
That takes us back to
our first image, and in
the Accessibility checker,
again, it gives us kind of this
Why Fix? and Steps to Fix.
It's saying that if
the image or object
is not inline, it may be
difficult for a screen reader
or assisted technology users
to find it in your document
and can make it a little
harder to interact with.
Usually, the easiest fix
here is to always use the
inline text wrapping.
The image I just opened the
Layout options, I can also go
to the Picture Format tab
of the ribbon and choose my
text wrapping options there.
Let's mark it as
In Line with text.
That's one more error down.
While we're still talking about
that, I do want to mention
another tidbit of information.
While in line is the generally
recommended and better option
for accessibility, there may
be scenarios where another
text wrapping option does
suit your document better.
Maybe if there's columns
or things like that.
If that's the case, some
of these other text
wrapping options can work
as long as there's a couple
other steps you take.
So let's do square text
wrapping, for example.
Some of these other text
wrapping options just give us
a little bit more flexibility
in how that image is placed.
So we have that error
again about the image or
object not being inline.
You may notice that
there's an anchor icon
in the left margin of my
document alongside the image.
That's a solution
that can improve the
accessibility of these
other text wrapping options.
The anchor basically indicates
where in your document the
image should be read,
and that way it does
get discovered by
assistive technology so
the user would find it.
And I can basically click and drag
that anchor to wherever I want it.
So maybe I wanted this image
to be talking about why the
Amazon Rainforest matters,
so I can drag it down now,
and now that means the
image will be read out to
a user right around the
same time they are reading
all that information.
That said, the in-line text
wrapping is the best option.
So we'd recommend that
wherever possible.
So one more down.
We have one more error
and one more warning here.
Our error looks like it's in
the table that's up above.
I have included this
table that is basically
a percentage of the Amazon
Rainforest contained in
South American countries.
Brazil has almost 60%;
Columbia about 7%; Argentina
and Chile have 0%.
So they don't have any
of the Amazon Rainforest
in their borders.
This error is calling out that my
table doesn't have a header row.
It looks like it does.
I have my country header
and my percentage of
Amazon Rainforest header.
But it's not quite there.
This error is referring to the
kind of semantic structure of it.
And so in assistive technology,
basically, looks at the markup
or the semantic structure
of the table to convey
certain relationships,
such that if a user is
moving between columns,
they would get the appropriate
row or column header read out.
It's always good to add
a header row to a table.
Let's go ahead and do that.
I will select my table.
I can either mark it as a
lay out table that's
intended to lay out content.
I think that's fairly
a new feature actually.
The main option is Use
first row as header.
In a down [phonetic]
table, that's usually the
most common approach that
the column headers are
at the very first row,
and so we can just make
that change in line.
There's no visual change to
that, but it does make the mark
up just a little more clear
for someone using assistive
technology to read through it.
I can also do that manually
in the table design tab of
the ribbon when I have the
table selected, I'd be able
to select that first row and
check Header Row here and any
other information I'd like
to convey in that table, I
can check appropriately.
The critical one's just
making sure you have
that header row marked.
Now we have a warning
here about merged or
split cells in the table.
I made a couple edits to
this table when I was
building it that intended
to make it a little bit
easier to consume, but
it does make the table
structure slightly more complex.
And why that's problematic
is when someone's using
assistive technology,
they would be navigating up
or down in the column and
then bouncing between columns.
So let's say I've gone through
the first five rows of the
table and the format is, okay,
I get my country, and then to
the right of it, I get the
percentage, country, percentage;
I get down here,
I'm on Guyana, and then
I move over to the next cell
and then I get French Guyana.
That's a little confusing
because someone was expecting
to get a percentage there
and might be wondering why that
structure's a little bit funky.
Let's go ahead
and change that.
I intentionally grouped
these on the same line, but
let's separate them out.
So I'm just getting rid of the
-- fixing [phonetic] those.
I've added my second row;
I'm going to use the Merge
column feature, great.
As I worked through
that, you may
have noticed that in the
accessibility checker those
errors slowly went away.
So great, so that's one more
error down, and then it's
telling us that this cell has 0%
in it, is another merged
cell which can impact
the experience for
someone with a disability.
So they recommend just
having unique lines for
each row in the table.
Let's go ahead and split that
cell, let's turn it into two rows.
Now I've added my 0% in
Argentina as well as Chile now.
Cool.
And you may now notice back
in the accessibility
checker, it says no
accessibility issues found.
People shouldn't have issues
reading this document.
While we're on the subject,
I wanted to briefly touch on
another best practice, another
couple best practices in here.
Back to my agenda slide,
there's one on heading structure.
I did already cover
conveying information by
color alone, but let's take
a look at hyperlinks,
and then we'll do a couple
things in PowerPoint.
So in this document,
I have some links here.
I have this one that says
"click here," and under
my Deforestation heading,
I have another link that
says "click here."
Using assistive technology,
the user may get confused by that.
The way a link would be read
like that is it would just
read, "link, click here."
And so it would read "link, click
here" and then "link, click here."
So it's difficult for a
user to differentiate what
those links are pointing to.
Let's give them a little
bit more descriptive name.
I think my hyperlink went to
Wikipedia, let me just copy that.
Let me craft a new sentence
and we can try it out, and
I can get rid of that one.
So now I made a new sentence
that reads "Check out
the link Wikipedia article on the
Amazon Rainforest to learn more."
So I said the word
"link" in there just
to indicate how an assistive
technology would read it.
So when we use that kind
of descriptive link,
that's very clear.
A user knows right away where
it's supposed to take them
and doesn't have to guess.
So let's go ahead and remove
that previous sentence.
That's better.
Let me again cut the
hyperlink, and let's do
the same thing down here -
this is my section
on deforestation.
Now I added, "Visit this
page for link more
statistics on deforestation.
Not only are the links
themselves more descriptive
and the user knows where
they are going to go.
If someone's navigating
link to link, they now
know which is which.
So that's the other
important factor there.
So next I mentioned I was
going to cover headings.
And so, in this document,
it's broken out into sections.
So the very beginning, I
have a document title "The
Amazon Rainforest," I have
a heading for "Deforestation,"
"Why it Matters," and "So,
what can you do?"
But for those of you who
are Word power users,
you may know that when you
add true heading styles from
the style section of the
ribbon, they can look
a certain way, but they also get
added to the Navigation pane.
So you may notice that I have
one item in the navigation
pane, a Bibliography.
When I select that in styles
tab of the ribbon, it's
using a Heading 1 style.
Headings are really
important for conveying the
structure of your document.
Let's go ahead and add some
headings to the document -
add some heading styles,
because I already have where
my section headers are.
So with this first one,
"The Amazon Rainforest," we select
that, I'll mark that
as a heading level 1.
It now shows up in the
navigation pane, it adds
some other heading
features, such as being
able to expand or collapse.
And then so the way
headings work is -
Heading 1 indicates the start
of the content or kind of the
main area of my content.
Heading 1 is always kind
about the main body.
Within that main body,
I have section headings.
So within the body, I would
make all of my section
headings a Heading 2.
So "Deforestation" and
Why it Matters" would both
be Heading 2 because they're
subsections of the Heading 1.
In this "Why it
Matters" section -
or sorry - I have one more
here, "So, what can you do?"
We also make that a Heading 2.
As I do that, these get
added to the navigation pane.
I have one more here --
"Here are some ideas."
So in the Heading 2 of "So,
what you can do," there's a
section of some specific ideas.
So I would say that's a subsection
of "So, what can you do?"
Let me mark that
as a Heading 3.
You kind of see my
heading structure get
built out a little bit.
For someone who is using
assistive technology,
they are able to navigate
just by headings.
So using a clean heading
structure like this, that
is indicating the layout
of the content, gives them
some idea of how best
they can most efficiently
read through my content.
And it's always a good practice
to only have one Heading 1.
There's a couple
exceptions to that.
In this document, for example,
that makes the most sense.
So let's select our Bibliography
and mark it a Heading 2.
So now everything in the document
is a subsection of the main body.
I can expand or
collapse these.
So they're a really cool
way to clean up my -- if I
have a really long document.
You may notice that the
headings weren't indicated in
the accessibility checker.
Today, I think the only error the
accessibility checker flags are -
I think it's a tip that's just
kind of a recommendation, is
if you have a really long
document, like over ten pages,
I'm not sure what the exact rule
of thumb is, but when you have
really long documents, it's going
to recommend that you add
headings to make it easier
to consume that document.
That's one example of
something that we didn't
cover but would show
up in the accessibility
checker in some scenarios.
Back to my status bar
in the lower left, we
now have this icon that says
Accessibility Good to go.
Now that we've done
a lot of these -
fixed the accessibility
checker errors and warnings
and tips and done some
of these other best practices,
it's telling us that our
document should be a good
experience for users.
So great, we made some good
progress on that Word document.
Let's switch back
over to PowerPoint.
And so I have this PowerPoint
open so let me close out of it.
There's a couple things
I want to call out here.
A lot of the things that I
covered in Word pretty much
apply one to one to Outlook.
There's some
exceptions to that.
There's some nuances to the
format the PowerPoint is that
makes it a little bit different.
As opposed to how the sequence
in which someone reads a
document, it is very linear.
The document is read top to
bottom, someone can navigate
section by section, where
at the core of
it, you don't have
to do anything special
to control the reading
order other than just put
the content in the
sequence that you want.
PowerPoint's a
little bit different.
There is this idea of slide
reading order in PowerPoint, and
so let's take a look at that.
I'm going to open up the
accessibility checker in
PowerPoint, and you can access
the same three ways,
either the review tab, the item
in the status bar,
or under File Info.
There are two errors called
out in this slideshow.
So this slide is telling
me I should check
my slide reading order,
so let's go ahead and try that.
Let's verify the object order.
So this - the way that this slide
would be read is picture five
and then the alt text
which is something about
a woman with illustrative question
marks above her to indicate ideas
and then a text box
with the text questions.
So this reading order pain
shows the sequence in which
someone's going to consume that.
This is a pretty simple
slide, but imagine a
pretty complex slide where
the important information is
kind of read out of order.
In this case, the visual
order that maybe a sighted
user would see in this slide,
is they would be drawn
to the text Questions.
And then they would see the
image as a supplemental piece.
So by that logic our
reading order is just a
little bit backwards here.
The text box should be read
first, and the picture
should be read second.
So we can just click and
drag that order or can use
the up and down arrows -
buttons to move those.
Great, so that changed our
reading order, and that reading
order issue got cleared
off of the slide because
it knows I went in and
validated the reading order
that was already there.
The next error that it's calling
out is a missing slide title.
That's a really similar
idea to headings in Word,
but a little bit different.
So in PowerPoint,
I have seen slide titles here.
If I go to my reading order
pane, I can show you those.
This one is title text
box 1 and then the text
on my next slide, Agenda, I have
a title text box that says Agenda
in it, and then my heading here
is a text box that says Thank You.
And so, when someone's
navigating through the list
of slides, the slide title is
the first thing that's read.
So I would hear things like
slide two agenda, on this slide,
it would just say
slide four because
my question slide would just say
slide four because I haven't
defined the title text box.
Let's go ahead and fix that.
In this case, it's just a
text box that says Questions.
So let's switch back to
the accessibility checker,
we'll select that object.
When I selected it, it switched
us to outline view, and
in outline view,
under each slide, you get kind
of a text on the slide,
but at the top level,
you get the slide title.
This slide looks blank because
there's no slide title applied.
Again, as someone is reading
through, they would hear,
slide one and the slide title;
slide two and the slide
title, and then down
on slide four,
they would just hear slide four.
Let's apply a title.
It selected the first object
on my slide and asked me
do I want to make
that a slide title?
Do I want to add my own
slide title or do I want to
add a hidden slide title?
I'll talk about these
in a little detail.
Starting with the bottom
one, Add a Hidden Slide
Title, some slides, there's
not really a natural title per
se that would show visually.
For example, if there's a page
with several visualizations or
things like that or
a process diagram, maybe
we don't want a visual
title text box because
that could distract from
what we're trying to convey.
If I add a hidden slide
title, it will basically
just add a text box just off
of the slide that won't show,
but lets me add a slide title.
Because it's adding an object, the
accessibility checker did ask us
to validate the
reading order again.
That's one option, again,
if I type Questions here,
that covers the slide title.
However, even though
it's appearing
offscreen, the title that
I've now applied would still be
read by assistive technology.
Someone would be getting
that information twice.
So this option is good
if there's not really a
logical spot for a title on
a slide, but you still want
to add one because it does
make it a better experience.
The other one is Add a Slide
Title which, basically, just adds
a title text box back to the slide
layout and lets me add text to it.
There's also Set
as Slide Title.
Let's do that.
That makes it even easier.
I don't have to add anything;
I can just select the
existing text box and
say make that a title.
So now in my outline view,
my slide title shows up, and
so now when someone lands
on this slide, they would
hear, slide four, questions.
Accessibility checker says
there's no more issues, and
my reading order
pane is good to go.
My title is first,
and then the image is second.
One other thing that I'll
mention is if I add my
own slide here, let's say
I want to just add a slide
with Resources and I'm going
to insert a couple shapes.
Just do a really quick
demonstration here.
So I've added just
some random stuff.
I have a header, a slide title,
an arrow, and another text box.
I switch back to my accessibility
checker; it's telling me I need
the alt text to that.
So let me do that real quick.
That I'll mark as
decorative, that arrow there.
Let's say I got rid of my slide
title text box altogether, and let
me add just one
more text box here.
So again, it caused an
issue with my slide title,
so let me fix that.
But I now have this issue with
Check reading order again.
So when I create my own
custom slides like that,
when I add information to
the slide, they're basically
added in the order -
the reading order is based on
the order by which those objects
were added to the slide.
So I've added that
Resources text box last.
And so because I didn't use
a built-in layout, it does make me
validate the reading order anyway.
As you can see, it's
made the title the last
object because that was
the last added object when
it converted from a text
box to a title field.
I do have to do some extra
steps if I use a custom layout.
If I use a predefined
layout such
as this two-content layout,
delete that slide and re-add it.
Let me do a new slide
Layout, Two Content, so I
can add resources, and then
I can add that same image
here and the text here.
The built-in slide layouts
just automatically define
my reading order for me.
So I don't have to
do anything extra
there, unless I drastically
want things to be read in a
different order.
This is a couple
recommendations
on the accessibility checker
and reading order in PowerPoint.
Similar idea, but a
couple just nuances there
unique to PowerPoint.
Switching back to my agenda
slide, I want to quickly
cover a couple other things.
In Outlook, I can select
Prefer Accessible Content, and
so I'll show you what
that looks like here.
Let me draft an email to
my colleague Larry, who I
know has configured this.
He configured it
yesterday, at least.
Let me try that again.
Okay, well I'm getting an
error message that says can't
show MailTips right now.
So there goes that demo.
But what mail I will what that
what MailTips is referring to
are these messages right
above your send and from
and to controls in
Outlook, and so
you may have noticed things like
someone being out of the office.
That's usually
considered a MailTip.
If someone's outside of your
organization, there's another
MailTip that will show there.
If I've added some
inaccessible content
and Larry has said he
prefers accessible
content, this status bar -
the MailTip will show up
one of recipients prefers
accessible content and gives
a call to action
on how to fix that.
That's a good way to make
sure you're receiving
accessible content.
To set that up, you do need
to go to Outlook on the web,
and so I have that open here.
I'm going into Settings, View all
Settings, General, Accessibility,
and then check Ask senders to
send content that's accessible.
Again,
now if someone is sending to
me something inaccessible,
they would be prompted to
make it accessible.
It doesn't identify the
specific users, that's an
intended behavior, again, due
to privacy you
don't want to say
a specific user prefers
accessible content because
that can imply that
they maybe have a disability.
But it would show up if
there's multiple recipients,
it may be clear.
It's still useful to
know that info I guess.
Just to show a couple
resources real quick, there
are several help articles
on the excessively checker such
as how to use it, and then there
are some specific articles for
each application, even broken down
by platform, so there may
be some slight differences in how
the accessibility checker works
in Word online versus
Word on the desktop.
And there's dedicated
articles for that.
And all of that's
on our Office Accessibility
Center, and so that's
aka.ms/officeaccessibility.
I'll show you those
links in a minute.
Kind of have this section
on make your content
accessible to everyone.
There's some videos and
stuff about each platform.
And then they have
articles specific to each
application and platform.
So Sway on the Web may have
some different behaviors with the
accessibility checker than Word.
So definitely recommend
checking that out.
Similar to the accessibility
checker is a tool called
Accessibility Insights,
and it's a tool that's able
to look at web content and
return some accessibility
issues that are found -
similar idea, but it's
looking at some web
accessibility standards and
is comparing the experience
against those standards.
They have a web extension,
so I'll show that in a second.
They also have an app for checking
Android, apps for accessibility
and then checking Windows
apps for accessibility.
Let me show you what that
Accessibility Insights looks like.
So I've opened a page from the
W3C World Wide Web Consortium.
They kind of set a lot
of the standards and
all that for the Web.
Let's run a quick check here
and see if any issues come up.
So I now have my Accessibility
Insights icon in my extensions
area of my web browser.
It looks like a little shield
with a magnifying glass icon.
So let me select FastPass, that's
going to do a quick automated
check, and that's looking
at the page,, and it's going to
tell me where there are issues.
So in this case,
there is one issue.
There's a link on their
page that doesn't have
a name, and it shows you
that object on the page.
This is useful if you're
creating a lot of web content
or you're a web developer,
things like that.
Just to really keep
in your back pocket.
Similarly to the accessibility
checker, it doesn't catch all
possible issues, but it is
a really good starting point
to get a good idea where
your accessibility is at.
So this is one that we
would recommend that
they fix on their site.
So that's Accessibility
Insights.
With that, I want to wrap
up and just share a couple
of those links again.
So first our accessibility
team has a Twitter MSFTenable
if you want to follow
us and learn more.
There's one of the areas
I mentioned, The Office
Accessibility Center
was aka.ms/OfficeAccessibility,
and then we also have
Accessibility fundamentals which
is a program on
docs.microsoft.com where you
can learn some of the
basics of accessibility.
There's a few different modules,
and you can get a badge that
you are able to display on your
social media, such as LinkedIn.
We strongly recommend doing
that, and the link is
aka.ms/AccessibilityFundamentals.
And I'm part of our part
of our Enterprise Disability
Answer Desk which supports
enterprise customers
that have accessibility
questions.
Governments and banks and other
businesses and things like that,
so we work a lot
with customers.
So if you want to learn
more about that and if you
are in a role that interfaces
a lot with customers, you may
want to reach out and just kind
of get to know us and
see how we can help.
You can learn more
at aka.ms/eDAD.
Enterprise Disability
Answer Desk.
With that, I think we
have some time for some
questions from you all.
>> Hey, Sean.
>> Yeah.
>> We have a few questions,
so I'm going to get started.
This question was from David.
I'm surprised accessibility
checker doesn't flag learn more
and other ambiguous hyperlinks
as such, it's such a
big case in documents.
>> Yeah, that's a valid point.
So awhile back there
used to be a rule
in the accessibility
checker that would flag
link purpose, and it was
if links were ambiguous
or not clear or if
the URL was really long and
was not discernible that way.
That rule was taken out
because putting URLs directly
in documents and PowerPoints
isn't inherently problematic like
these aka links or if I
type Microsoft.com, that's
a pretty clear
link, but if I do
a very long string or URL,
then it gets pretty cumbersome.
There's not a way today
to check for link names
like click here or learn
more, learn more, but I
think that's something the
team has been exploring.
But it's certainly feedback
that we'll pass on.
>> All right. Thanks.
There's one more question.
It's from Vanessa.
It's if I export a PPT to
PDF, will the accessibility
content export what it?
>> Yeah,
and I can show that real quick.
That's a great question.
Let me just clean up
my slides a little bit.
So I've gone in and as we did
on this walk-thru and improved
all the accessibility issues here.
Now, yeah, it is pretty
easy to export even Word
documents or this to PDF.
So I'll go to File.
Now, I know a lot of folks
use Print and save as PDF.
We actually don't want
to do that route because
that, today, doesn't keep a
lot of that accessibility
markup that we've added.
So I would either do Save
As or Export and Create PDF.
>> Hang on one second.
I realize I didn't
share the screen.
Sorry.
>> That's okay.
So I've gone into
PowerPoint again, I've
gone to File, Export, PDF,
and then Create PDF,
and then I can title it.
I want to call out
the options here.
There's this checkbox for
document for including
the document structure tags
for accessibility purposes.
That's checked by default.
But just be aware that's
there, and it's
a good thing to
validate if you want
to output an accessibility
PDF, make sure that's checked.
And then it is really easy.
So you would just
then hit Publish.
So it's pretty easy
and straightforward to
make accessible PDFs.
From Word,
it's the same process.
Just make sure you make
it accessible through the
accessibility checker
and then export it
as a PDF as opposed to
printing it as a PDF.
Great question.
>> There's quite
a few questions.
We'll try to get as
much as we could.
You ready for the next one?
>> Sure.
>> This is from Jane,
and the question is: Do
you have any guidelines
on when to add alt
description for
an image changing to descriptive
decorator and for decorative.
Would you then exclude
these from the slide order?
>> That's a good question
on PowerPoint too.
With imagens, my general rule
is they're conveying content
and they are meaningful
and someone would gain information
from that image, you want
to add good alt
text to describe it.
If the image is not adding
a lot of content, such as
on this last slide, my
image of the woman with the
question marks above her head.
That one has alt text, but
that would actually be okay
to mark as decorative.
And then in my reading order
pane, let me bring that back up.
When I mark something
as decorative,
it automatically gets deselected
from the reading order.
From the reading order pane,
I can also mark stuff as
decorative really easily
if I just check or uncheck it.
So now it's not decorative
again, and you'd want
to make sure it has
alt text in that case.
And then if I uncheck
it, it marks it
as decorative and then hides
it from the reading order.
Good question.
>> Okay, cool.
Do you have time
for a few more?
>> Sure.
>> Okay,
so this is from David again.
In PowerPoint polish EBC decks
and exec decks [phonetic]
often have complex visuals
with a lot of little pieces
like the lines, dots, etc.
What is the guidance for alt
text, decorative, etc.?
Is there a way to group
everything together within a
slide in a hidden way that can
be grouped together with a
single description or other
best practices in these cases?
>> Sure, that's a really
good question and something
we do actually see a lot.
There's lots of scenarios
where someone might
have really complicated visuals
that have lots of objects.
Whenever possible, we
recommend simplifying
that as much as you can.
If you don't need quite so
many of the objects, you
can hide them, mark
them as decorative, but
you can group things.
That helps a lot.
So these slides I have
today aren't very complex
so I don't have a
great example here, but
if I had a really complex slide,
I could group the objects together
and then in the reading
order pane, they would
show in that group.
If it's a really complex visual
that just has lots of pieces but
it's indicating one thing,
one approach that I've seen
a lot is if you select each
of those objects that are
conveying one thing, copy
cutting them from the slide
and then pasting them as
an image and then giving
that image alt text -
because if the goal is for
your visual to have just kind
of one key take away from it,
as much as you can do
that, kind
of distill it down into one
image and give alt text to that.
I don't have a great example.
Let me see if I can mock
one up just really quick.
I'll just add a
couple symbols.
>> I think there was
a follow-up to that.
So let me keep reading.
The desired outcome is
that each line and dot
would be considered in and
of itself decorative,
but the sum
of all the little components
would be a single visual ID.
What is [indiscernible]
to give a description for?
Anyway to achieve
this outcome?
>> Yeah, so in what
I'm creating right now.
Let's say that I've just
added a simple chart,
but maybe these triangles
are indicating some sort
of up and down diagram,
trend or something like that.
But each of them is
a discrete object.
So what I can do is I'll cut them
from the slide and then paste them
as image and so
now they're still
the same visual but it's just
one object to give alt text.
>> Yeah,
but the only challenge is that -
and, again, this coming from David
- the only challenge is that if
we paste it as image, you
lose ability to animate
the complex diagram.
>> Yeah, I think to be
transparent, there's not
a perfect answer that I can
give today, unfortunately.
Whenever possible, make those
things as flat as you can, and so
if there are things that
animate in together, maybe
those could be a group.
But just wherever possible,
think about how you can reduce
the number of discrete
objects, either by grouping
or pasting as image.
I know that's not a great
answer, but --
>> Okay, thanks Sean.
A lot of great questions.
We are right about on time
so I want to wrap this.